Guide to the Jan H. Boer Collection on Christian-Muslim Relations in Nigeria
Yale University Divinity School Library
Jan H. Boer Collection on Christian-Muslim Relations in Nigeria
1950-2008
1975-2008
RG 228
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(19 boxes)
These papers are part of the sources gathered by Jan H. Boer for the writing of his eight-volume series Studies in Christian-Muslim Relations. The collection deals almost exclusively with the Nigerian situation, especially the entire history leading up to the sharia declaration and its aftermath. The materials include Nigerian magazines and newspaper clippings as well as scholarly articles and lectures, essays, and conference papers from Christian, Muslim and secular perspectives.
Boer, Jan Harm
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jan H. Boer, 2010, 2014
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Jan H. Boer is a Dutch Canadian, who during his early teens immigrated to British Columbia, Canada, with his parental family. He studied theology at Calvin Theological Seminary in Grand Rapids, Michigan (1962-1965) and did African Studies at Michigan State University. He served in various capacities listed on his website as a seconded missionary of the combo Christian Reformed World Missions and Sudan United Mission, most of the time with the Institute of Church and Society, Jos, Nigeria. He sat for several months at the feet of the young Lamin Sanneh in Ibadan in 1967. During his Nigeria years, he also took time off to obtain a doctorate from the Free University of Amsterdam, where he studied under Prof. Johannes Verkuyl and obtained his degree on basis of his Missionary Messengers of Liberation in a Colonial Context: A Case Study of the Sudan United Mission (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1979, 530 pages).
Scope and Contents
These archives were developed by Boer for his own private use. The organization is based mostly on year of publication. Within each year the materials have been divided according to format or genre, e.g. Papers/essays/printous (includes photocopies from books and web printouts as well as typescript papers, etc.), Newspaper articles, Magazine articles, Letters/emails/printouts. The format categories overlap. Of use in discovering materials within these folders is a set of notes compiled by Boer for materials dated 2000-2008. These notes are available in digital form on a CD contained in the final folder of the collection (Box 13, folder 11). Keyword searching of the notes for each year will enable the researcher to make connections with the documents available in the collection.
Additional notes, writings, clippings, articles, and books were received in 2014 and are organized in Series III, Addendum.
An overview of Boer's eight-volume work, Studies in Christian-Muslim Relations (Belleville, Ont.: Essence Pub.), is available at http://www.socialtheology.com/islamica.htm.
Arrangement
I. Documentation of Christian-Muslim Relations in Nigeria, 1950-2008
II. Boer Notes on Documentation, 2000-2008
III. Addendum - 2015
Islam -- Relations -- Christianity; Christianity and other religions -- Islam; Islamic law -- Nigeria; Religion and politics -- Nigeria -- History -- 20th Century; Religion and politics -- Nigeria -- History -- 21st century; Boer, Jan Harm
- Documentation of Christian-Muslim Relations in Nigeria, 1950-2008; Series I
  - 1950-1960s
    - Papers/essays: "Religion of Islam", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Papers/essays: "Nigeria Background to Nationalism"; "Design of My World"; "Studies in Islam", 1958, 1962, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - News articles, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1970s
    - Papers/essays: "The Aristotelian and Islamic Concepts of Slavery"; "Social Justice in Islam and the Muslim Countries"; "Political Role of Islam in West Africa"; "Second Islamic Conference of Foreign Ministers – text of the Address of General Agha Muhammad Yahya Khan"; "Democracy: Greek, Roman and Islamic Concepts", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Papers/essays: "Islamic Culture and Socio-Economic Change"; "Religion and Political Culture in Kano"; "Islam and the Confluence of Religions in Uganda 1840-1966"; "Charter of the Islamic Conference"; "Modern Trends in Islam", 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Papers/essays: "Human Rights in Islamic Law"; "A Draft Constitution for Nigeria", 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Papers/essays: "How Islamic are Nigerian Laws"; "The Constituent Assembly A Case for a Canon Law Courts System in Nigeria" "Notes by I.S. Usman"; 'The Role of Education", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Papers/essays: "Religious Pluralism and the Draft Constitution for Nigeria"; "The Hour of Decision: Sharia or Jihad (Chaos)"; "Islam in Focus d. Education and Nation Building", 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Papers/essays: "Society and State in Islam An Introduction", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1980s
    - Papers/essays: "Major Themes of the Qur'an"; "Islam From Within"; "Quotable Quotes of Alhaji Bashir Othman Fofa"; "Moslims onze nieuwe landgenoten", 1980, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Papers/essays: "Islamic Life and Thought"; "Islam in Transition"; "Jesus More than a Prophet"; "Letter concerning Religious Disturbance of 10/30/82", 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Magazine articles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Papers/essays: "Non-Muslims in Islamic State: Their Rights and Privileges"; "In Search of Meaning and Identity: Conversion to Christianity in Pakistani Muslim Culture" ;"Observations on the Interpretation of the Concept of Religious Freedom in Christianity and Islam"; "Letter to Arch Bishop Peter Jatau", 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Papers/essays: "Religious Tolerance and Peaceful Coexistence Among Nigerians"; "Religious Disturbances in Nigeria"; "Islam, Secularism and Nigeria", 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - News articles, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Papers/essays:: "Religious Tolerance in Islam", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - News articles, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Magazine articles, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Papers/essays: "In the Name of God"; "Worshippers of Baal"; "Islam and the Muslim Community"; "Islamic Liberation Movement"; "Borneo State Council of Understanding"; "The Church and the Government as Partners in Progress"; "The 1987 Kaduna State Religious Disturbances"; "Relationship Between the Police Force and Christians in Plateau State"; "A Catalogue of Atrocity" (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - News articles, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Magazine articles, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Papers/essays: "Is This Islam (Politics in Religion); "Human Rights and Islam"; "Directorate for Social Mobilization"; "Islamisation of the Country Through the Nigeria Police Force"; "A Meeting of the Action Committee of Tekan"; "Construction of a Mosque at Government House"; "Call 'The New Nigerian' Newspapers and Agents of Destabilization to Order Now", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - News articles, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Magazine articles, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Papers/essays: "Neighbors: Muslims in North America"; "Islam and Human Rights"; "Fulani Muslims Follow Christ"; "Proposals for Restoration of Religious Peace"; "Erection of Religious Building in the L.G.C. Secretariat"; "Paper Presented to General Ibrahim Babangida"; "On Christian Moslem Relation in Nigeria", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Papers/essays: "Conference on Christian Worldview- Address"; "The Prospects for Sharia in Nigeria"; "Islam in Africa"; "Da'wah in Africa and the Question of Methods"; "Da'wa and the Challenge of Secularism"; "Shura as an Integral Aspect of Political System in Islam"; "Aspects of Politicization of Religion in Nigeria and the Roles of N.A.S.R. and Nareto", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - News articles, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Magazine articles, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1990s
    - Letters and Papers/essays: "Letter to Ibrahim B. Babangida"; "J. Hudson Taylor and Samuel Zwemer Mission Pioneers"; "Egypt's Religious Minorities Face Islamic Dominance"; "Turkey to Clarify Religious Rights"; "Algerian Movie Review"; "Iraqi Aggression Stirs Northern 'Condominium' to Action"; "The Third Eye", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - News articles, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Papers/essays: "The Last Resort for Christians in Nigeria is Resistance or Self-Defence"; "Striving Together-A Way Forward in Christian-Muslim Relations"; "Promoting Religious Peace and Security in Nigeria"; "War Against Christians"; "Victorian Images of Islam f. Premeditated Killing of Innocent People in Kano"; "Islamic Forum of Nigeria-Summary of Decisions Reached"; "The Truth About Uniformed People Christian Fellowship"; "Statement Issued by the National Executive Committee", 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Magazine articles, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - News articles, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Papers/essays: " The Kaduna State Religious Riot"; "Bishop Josiah Feason's Comment": "The Southern Kaduna Question"; "Personal Recommendations to the Tribunal"; "Two Faces of Islam The Lessons of a Modern Sufi Manual", 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Magazine articles, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - News articles, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Papers/essays: "Islamic Fundamentalism: The Shias in Katsina", 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Papers/essays:"The Enduring Revolution"; "The Draft Constitution"; "Problems of Corruption, Politics and Religion in the Nigerian Society"; "A Global Ethic: The Declaration of the Parliament of the World's Religions", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Magazine articles, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - News articles, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Papers/essays: "At What Kind of Understanding are we Aiming in Christian-Muslim Dialogue"; "Dialogue Between Muslims and Christians"; "Dialogue Between Christians and Muslims in Nigeria: How Feasible?"; "The Theology of God's Word from the Biblical and Qur'anic Perspective"; "The Role of Faith in Religious Dialogue"; "The Influence of Politics on Religious Dialogue", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Papers/Letters: "Beyond Liberation Theology"; Letter to John Boer from Jurgen Quack, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Magazine articles, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - News articles, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters/Papers" "National Council on US-Arab Relations"; "The Malcolm H. Kerr High School Scholars Program in Arab and Islamic Studies"; "The Hidden Agenda d. Letter to Emman Usman Shehu from Jan Boer"; "The Western Mind of Radical Islam"; "First, Second and Third in Nongo Kristu U Sudanhen Tiv"; Letter to All Staff at CPJ from John Boer, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Magazine articles, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - News articles, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - The Second International Conference on Christian-Muslim Mutual Relations: "Justice and Peace The Qur'anic Perspective"; "Justice and Peace from the Biblical Perspective"; "Secularism and Religious Pluralism A Christian View"; "Secularism versus Multi-religion. A Muslim View"; "Inter-Religious Dialogue-Cordiality and Divine Love"; "Biblical Teaching on the Love of God and its Implication for Dialogue between Christians and People of Other Faiths"; "The Christian View of Forgiveness Implications for Christian-Muslim Dialogue"; Address by Sheikh Dahiru Bauchi; "God's Mercy in the Bible"; "God and His Mercy in the Holy Qur'an"; "Why Do We Experience Fanaticism? A Muslim View"; "Why is it that we Experience Fanaticism? A Christian View"; "The Importance of our Moral Conscience in Improving our Co-Existence: The Muslim View"; "The Importance of Moral Conscience in Improving Co-Existence Between Christians and Muslims: The Christian Perspective", 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Papers/essays: "Three Nigerian Christian Schools Closed for not Teaching Islam"; "Human Rights Abuses in Nigeria", 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Magazine articles, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - News articles, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Letters/Papers/essays: "An Analysis to Time Allocated for Christian Versus Muslim Programmes for Selected States in Northern Nigeria", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Magazine articles, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - News articles, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - MA thesis: "The Rise of Islamic Fundamentalism in Northern Nigeria and its Impact on the Church as an Erector of the signs of God's Kingdom", 1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Magazine articles, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - News articles, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Magazine articles, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - News articles, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - News articles, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Papers/essays: "Zakzaky, Toro Oppose Sani on Sharia"; "A Communique Issued at the End of the Meeting of Zamfara State Chapter of Christian Association of Nigeria", 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 2000-2008
    - News articles, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Conference Papers at First National Seminar of the Nigeria Inter-Religious Council: "Understanding Christians and Muslims over the Adoption of the Full Scope of the Islamic Sharia Law in Nigeria"; "The Sharia Law and its Application in Nigeria"; "A Paper on Dialogue Between Muslims and Christians: Sharia Issues in Nigeria"; "The Sharia in Nigeria: Issues and Perspectives"; "The Constitutional and Legal Status of Sharia in Nigeria"; 2000 Annual Report on International Religious Freedom: Niger; "Center Testifies on Persecution in Saudi Arabia"; "Shariah: The Misunderstood Legal System" (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Papers/essays: "Sharia and the Constitution"; "Summary of Memoranda Submitted to the Committee on the Implications of Sharia on Christians and Non-Muslims in Gombe State"; "Minutes of the Meeting of 129 Northern States and Abuja"; "Minutes of Can Northern States and Abuja"; "A communiqué of the Christian Association of Nigeria (C.A.N.) Northern States and Abuja"; "Sharia in Nigeria: Its Meaning and Implication for Christians"; "The Sharia Issue: Working Papers for a Dialogue", 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - News articles, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Magazine articles, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Letters, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Magazine articles, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - News articles, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Magazine articles, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - News articles, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Audu Letters and Related News Articles, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2004 Jan-Jun (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - News articles, 2004 Jan-Jun (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Magazine articles, 2004 Jan-Jun (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2004 Jul-Dec (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - News articles, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Magazine articles, 2004 Jul-Dec (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, including from Jos International Conference on Comparative Perspectives on the Shari'ah in Nigeria, and ""Rejoinder to World Igbo Conference"; "North's New Ordeals: Killing in the Name of God"; "Dissecting Moral Decadence", etc., 2004 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - News articles, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, including "Adversary and Kukah in National Dialogue"; "People and Politics by Mohammed Haruna"; "Social Justice and Resource Control in Nigeria: a Crisis of Legitimacy", etc., 2005 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - News articles, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Magazine articles, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - News articles, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Magazine articles, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 6-8)
    - Magazine articles, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - News articles, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Re. conference: "Muslims, Political Violence and the Security Establishment", 2006 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Articles from Light Bearer, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Magazine articles, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - News articles, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Papers/essays/printouts: "Communique Issued by the Nigeria Inter-Religious Council (NIREC)"; "Don't Let Them Do This to Us: A Message to Nigerian Youths"l "Repositioning Religion, Faith and Ethics for a Sustainable Economic Transformation of the Nigerian People"; "Releasing the Trigger: The Nigeria Factor in Global Christianity"; "How to Reach Muslims with the Gospel"; "The Little Mosque that Couldn't"; "Whoever is Pro-Oha-Na-Eze's 2006 Declaration Speaks for Ndiigbo: It is That Simple"; "It is Against Bdigbo's Strategic Interest for Dr. Eddy Oparaoji to Liken Umaru Yaradua with Islamist"; "Plateau's Politics of Religion"; "Liberating Christianity"; "I Won't Die for Nigeria"; "G-S and Africa: Why do we Always to be Like Beggars", 2007 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Letters/email/printouts, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Magazine articles, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - News articles, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Magazine articles, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - News articles, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - No date
    - Letters/email/printouts, no date (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Papers/essays/printouts, including: "An Examination of Shaikh Adam Abdullah Al-Ilori's View on Religion and Politics"; "Political Order and the Plural Structure of Society"; "Political Shariah: Aren't the Fulanis Pushing Us to the Abyss"; "Sketch of the History of Shari'a"; "Christian-Muslim Dialogue: Its Historical Perspective in West Africa";"Christian Association of Nigeria National Executive Committee Communique on Recent Events in the Country"; "The Christian and the OIC w. Terrorism and Islamism – Politics in the Name of the Prophet"; etc., no date (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - News articles, no date (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Magazine articles, no date (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Boer Notes on Documentation, 2000-2008; Series II
  - CD contains notes by Boer re. documentation listed above, 2000-2008 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Addendum, Series III
  - Writings and notes of Boer
    - Notes, drafts, press releases re: Kaduna, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Draft Kaduna Hargitsin Addini '87, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Notes, drafts, correspondence re: Muslim-Christinan relations, 1994-2009 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Drafts re: Chrstianity, Islam vs. secularism, 2003-2005 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Notes, drafts re: Islam in Nigeria, 1992-2005 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Publications, 2001-2003 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Collected newspaper clippings
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1991-1999 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2008 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2009 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2010 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2012-2013 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Collected research papers and articles
    - Notes and research, 1997-1999 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Notes and research, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes CD-ROM The World of Islam: Resources for Understanding
    - Conferences, events and research, 2001-2003 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Newsletters, events and research, 2006-2008 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Colleagues published research, 1995-2003 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Colleagues published research, 1978-2003 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Magazines, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Magazines, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Magazine clippings, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Magazines, 1995-1996 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Magazine clippings, 1999-2004 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Magazine clippings, 2007-2008 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1995, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Collected books and pamphlets
    - English language books (Box 18, Folder 1)
      These are primarily duplicate copies of books held at Yale. Other titles received from Boer have been added to the Library's cataloged collection. Titles in this box include: Sharia in Nigeria: A Christian Perspective; African Religion Meets Islam; Politics and Religion in Nigeria; Christians in Nigerian Politics; The Tragedy of Sharia, Cry and the Voice of Masses; Towards the Right Path for Nigeria; Honourable Justice J.H. Dandaura: Apostle of Religious Harmony
    - African language books (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Titles include: Tarihin Ekklesiya; Linjila; Fassar Littafi Mai Tsarki Filibbiyawa; Fassarar Littafi Mai Tsarki Yohanna Ta Fari; Kirista Kuzo Muduba Mugani II; Alhajjul Mabrur; Rayuwan masu ciwon AIDS da iyalensu a cikin jama'a; Koyaswar Sabon Alkawali game da Ekklesiya; Babban Priest Mai Girma; Binciken Kolossiya Wa; Bible lessons and scripture in Hausa language; Compendium Catechism in Hausa
    - Proceedings and journals, 1974-1982 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Reports and case studies, 1999-2004 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Road and street maps of Nigeria, Lagos, Kaduna, Kano, 1964-1975 (Box 19, Folder 4)